A Guide to the Collaboratives for Humanities and Arts Teaching (CHART) records FA422
Rockefeller Archive Center
Collaboratives for Humanities and Arts Teaching (CHART) records
1984-1994
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation
Rényi, Judith
Collaboratives for Humanities and Arts Teaching
FA422
8.51 Cubic Feet 22 boxes: 18 document boxes, 3 half-boxes, and 1 flat box for photos.
Related Materials
Rockefeller Foundation Annual Reports, 1983-1993
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged materials are available at the discretion of RAC.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains materials related to the group Collaboratives for Humanities and Arts Teaching (CHART), a project of the Rockefeller Foundation that operated from 1983-1994. While a few documents come from as early as 1983 or as late as 1994, the bulk of the materials date between 1987 and 1993. Series 1 includes substantial correspondence from CHART director Judith Renyi to the Rockefeller Foundation, CHART site directors, and many others, as well as some additional planning materials. Major Rockefeller Foundation correspondents include Alberta Arthurs and Hugh B. Price. Series 2 contains details about potential CHART sites, the CHARTnet telecommunications network between teachers, the Africa in the U.S. Classroom project, and other reports on national education issues. This series also contains considerable information about the creation and publication of the CHART book, Fire in the Eyes of Youth, a copy of which text is in the public relations materials in box 21. Series 3 includes materials such as agendas, handouts, and transcripts from various conferences which CHART members either attended or helped to organize. Finally, series 4 houses many of CHART's public relations materials, including newspaper clippings and other media as well as formal information kits. Substantial content throughout the collection also relates to individual projects sponsored by CHART, such as Humanitas and PATHS. Overall, major topics covered include the humanities, the arts, multicultural and international education, school reform and restructuring, and the funding for such reforms.
Arrangement
The CHART records are arranged into the following four series: 1.Administration 2.Projects 3.Conferences and Institutes 4.Public Relations
The original arrangement of the documents was largely retained, except in cases where titles were clearly inaccurate or items clearly misfiled. The original reverse chronological order was retained at the item level (and documents were occasionally rearranged to maintain this order), but alphabetical-chronological order was imposed at the folder level.
Four sheets of photographs and one cassette tape had to be removed from the main collection for preservation. The photographs are housed in oversize box 22, while the cassette tape has been removed to Special Formats.
Institutional History
Collaboratives for Humanities and Arts Teaching (CHART) was initiated in 1983 by the Rockefeller Foundation, although it did not formally adopt the name CHART until 1987. CHART began in response to the 1980 Rockefeller Foundation report "The Humanities in American Life," which warned of a crisis in American humanities education, and as a way to combat the "back to basics" pedagogy that predominated at the time and left students drilling and memorizing rather than learning and exploring. While they started with the goal of improving humanities education, CHART leaders soon realized that this goal was almost impossible to achieve without larger school reform, so they turned much of their attention to school restructuring and teacher-led curricular reform. This change was reflected in the movement of CHART out of the Rockefeller Foundation's arts and humanities division and into their relatively new school reform program in 1990. CHART's primary function was as a source of funding and an organizational umbrella for a variety of localized reform and education projects. The list below gives the name of each project, the year CHART began supporting it, and the year it ceased to be a CHART project. Common characteristics of all the CHART sites included localized, teacher-driven curricula, a focus on average students in urban or rural environments, and the expansion of multicultural and international education. Collaborations with other local institutions, such as museums, universities, and businesses, also formed a major element of many CHART projects. Collaboration between projects and among educators across the country was an essential element as well, as evidenced by the large number of conferences and institutes that CHART leaders attended or helped to run, including frequent meetings between all of the CHART site directors. The Rockefeller Foundation gave its tenth and final grant to CHART in 1993, and CHART formally ceased to exist as an entity in early 1994. The individual CHART project sites generally continued to operate after this time, and some connection between them may have been maintained, but this collection contains very little information pertaining to the formal end of CHART and the nature and specifics of the transfer of responsibility to individual sites.
CHART Project, Location, Years with CHART Advancing Teaching and Learning in Arkansas Schools (ATLAS), Arkansas, 1988-1993 Arts PROPEL, Pittsburgh, 1988-1993 CROSSROADS, Seattle, 1985-1988 DIALOGUE, St. Paul, 1984; 1986-1988 HUMANITAS, Los Angeles, 1986-1993 Humanities Education, Research and Learning Development (HERALD), San Francisco, 1988-1993 Inhabiting Other Lives, Miami, 1989-1993 International Education Consortium (IEC), St. Louis, 1985-1993 New Mexico CURRENTS, New Mexico, 1990-1993 New York and the World, NYC, 1986-1993 Philadelphia Alliance for Teaching Humanities in the Schools (PATHS), Philadelphia, 1983-1993 Renaissance Outreach Alliance for the Detroit Area Schools (ROADS), Detroit, 1989-1993 Rural Education Alliance for Collaborative Humanities (REACH), South Carolina, 1987-1993 Scholars United for Multicultural Inquiry in Teaching (SUMMIT), Colorado, 1990-1993 Superintendent's Academy for Humanities and Arts Teaching, D.C., 1989-1993 The Connecticut Humanities Alliance, Connecticut, 1989-1993 The National Faculty's Humanities Project, Atlanta, 1984-1986
Arts; Humanities; Education, Rural; Education, Urban; Rockefeller Foundation; Multicultural education; Public schools; Arts -- Study and teaching; Education -- United States; Educational change
- Adminstration, 1; 2.08 Cubic Feet 2 legal document boxes and 3 letter document boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series 1, Administration, contains mainly correspondence, which is separated into two categories: the director's general correspondence and correspondence with the Rockefeller Foundation. This series also contains a few folders of planning material, one report to the trustees, and a substantial amount of information from the President's Committee on Arts and Humanities.
  - Director Correspondence, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Director Correspondence, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Director Correspondence, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Director Correspondence, January-March 1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Director Correspondence, April-August 1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Director Correspondence, September-October 1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Director Correspondence, Mary-May 1993 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Director Correspondence, June-December 1993 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Director Correspondence: CHART Proposals and Reports, 1990, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Director Correspondence: Correspondence to Site Directors, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Director Correspondence: Correspondence to Site Directors, April-May 1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Director Correspondence: Correspondence to Site Directors, June-December 1990 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Planning: Research-Based, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Planning, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Planning (CLOSED), 1993 (Box 3, Folder 14A)
  - President's Committee on Arts and Humanities, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - President's Committee on Arts and Humanities, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - President's Committee on Arts and Humanities, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - President's Committee on Arts and Humanities, January-September 1990 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - President's Committee on Arts and Humanities, October 1990-April 1992 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - President's Committee on Arts and Humanities (CLOSED), October 1990-April 1992 (Box 3, Folder 19A)
  - President's Committee on Arts and Humanities, May 1992-January 1993 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Report to Trustees, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Correspondence, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Correspondence, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Correspondence, January-June 1989 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Correspondence, July-September 1989 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Correspondence, October-December 1989 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Correspondence, January-April 1990 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Correspondence, May-July 1990 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Correspondence, August-December 1990 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Correspondence, January-June 1991 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Correspondence, July-December 1991 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Correspondence, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Correspondence, January-July 1993 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Correspondence, August-November 1993 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Correspondence: CHART Principles, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Rockefeller Foundation Correspondence: Wolf, Connie, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 36)
- Projects, 2; 2.7 Cubic Feet 2 legal document boxes, 4 letter document boxes, and 1 half-legal document box
  Series 2, Projects, includes a variety of materials about several CHART efforts, including the Africa in the U.S. Classroom initiative, the CHARTnet telecommunications network, the legacy project, and the CHART book, Fire in the Eyes of Youth. Also included are details about several CHART-funded projects, such as conferences and surveys, and a number of exploratory proposals detailing potential future CHART sites.
  - Africa in the U.S. Classroom: Correspondence, 1989-1991 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Africa in the U.S. Classroom: Report, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Africa in the U.S. Classroom: Research: Background and Jacqz Report (1 of 2), 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Africa in the U.S. Classroom: Research: Background and Jacqz Report (2 of 2), 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Africa in the U.S. Classroom: Research: Final Report, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Africa in the U.S. Classroom: Seminar, 7-9 March 1990, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - CHART Funded Projects: American Federation of Teachers Quest Conference, 20 July 1989 (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - CHART Funded Projects: Freedman, Sarah, National Center for the Study of Writing and Literacy, 1990-1993 (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - CHART Funded Projects: Harvard Summer Institute, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - CHART Funded Projects: Matsushita/Rockefeller Foundation Evaluation Conference, 1989-1991 (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - CHART Funded Projects: Multicultural Survey, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - CHART Funded Projects: South Carolina Curriculum Congress, 1988-July 1991 (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - CHART Funded Projects: South Carolina Curriculum Congress, August 1991-January 1993 (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - CHART Funded Projects: South Carolina Curriculum Frameworks, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - CHARTnet: BreadNet News, 1989-1991 (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - CHARTnet: BreadNet Branches, 1990-1991 (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - CHARTnet: Network Correspondence, August 1990-February 1992 (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - CHARTnet Transcripts, September 1990-February 1991 (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - CHARTnet Transcripts, March-April 1991 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - CHARTnet Transcripts, May-November 1991 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - CHARTnet Transcripts, November 1991-April 1992 (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - CHARTnet Transcripts, May-December 1992 (Box 8, Folder 59)
  - CHARTnet Transcripts, January-March 1993 (Box 8, Folder 60)
  - Exploratory Proposals, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 61)
  - Exploratory Proposals, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 62)
  - Exploratory Proposals, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 63)
  - Exploratory Proposals: Baton Rouge, 1990-1992 (Box 9, Folder 64)
  - Exploratory Proposals: Boston, 1988-1990 (Box 9, Folder 65)
  - Exploratory Proposals: Center for the Liberal Arts, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 66)
  - Exploratory Proposals: Chattanooga, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 67)
  - Exploratory Proposals: Cincinnati, 1987-1988 (Box 10, Folder 68)
  - Exploratory Proposals: Cleveland, 1987-1989 (Box 10, Folder 69)
  - Exploratory Proposals: Common Destiny Alliance, 1991-1992 (Box 10, Folder 70)
  - Exploratory Proposals: Hawaii, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 71)
  - Exploratory Proposals: Lauter, Paul, 1991-1992 (Box 10, Folder 72)
  - Exploratory Proposals: Peace Development Fund, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 73)
  - Exploratory Proposals: San Antonio, October 1988-May 1989 (Box 10, Folder 74)
  - Exploratory Proposals: San Antonio, June 1989-March 1990 (Box 10, Folder 75)
  - Exploratory Proposals: Sent from Arthurs to Renyi for Review, 1988-1990 (Box 10, Folder 76)
  - Fire in the Eyes of Youth: Complimentary Copies Mailing List (1 of 3), 1993 (Box 11, Folder 77)
  - Fire in the Eyes of Youth: Complimentary Copies Mailing List (2 of 3), 1993 (Box 11, Folder 78)
  - Fire in the Eyes of Youth: Complimentary Copies Mailing List (3 of 3), 1993 (Box 11, Folder 79)
  - Fire in the Eyes of Youth: Contributor Correspondence, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 80)
  - Fire in the Eyes of Youth: Contributor Correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 11, Folder 81)
  - Fire in the Eyes of Youth: Distribution and Public Relations, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 82)
  - Fire in the Eyes of Youth: Jennings, Randy, Correspondence, 1991-1993 (Box 11, Folder 83)
  - Fire in the Eyes of Youth: Publication, 1992-1993 (Box 11, Folder 84)
  - Fire in the Eyes of Youth: Reviews, 1993-1994 (Box 12, Folder 85)
  - Legacy Project: Bibliographic Booklet, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 86)
  - Legacy Project: Jennings, Randy, General Correspondence, 1990, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 87)
  - Legacy Project: Humanitas Essays at Cleveland High, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 88)
  - Teacher Networks Group, November 1987-April 1988 (Box 12, Folder 89)
  - Teacher Networks Group, May-October 1988 (Box 12, Folder 90)
  - Teacher Networks Group, December 1988 (Box 12, Folder 91)
  - Teacher Networks Group, 1989-1991 (Box 12, Folder 92)
- Conferences and Institutes, 3; 2.27 box(es) 1 half-legal document box, 1 legal document box, 3 letter document boxes, and 1 oversize box
  Series 3, Conferences and Institutes, contains information from the large number of conferences that CHART leaders either attended or helped to plan between 1984 and 1993. Materials include agendas, handouts, and transcripts of discussions.
  - Conferences: CHART and School Restructuring, 11-14 October 1990 (Box 13, Folder 93)
  - Conferences: CHART Conference, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 94)
  - Conferences: CHART Conference, 25-27 March 1987, 1987 (Box 13, Folder 95)
  - Conferences: CHART Conference, 3-5 December 1987, 1987 (Box 13, Folder 96)
  - Conferences: CHART Directors' Conference, 13-14 October 1992, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 97)
  - Conferences: CHART Directors' Meeting, 12-13 May 1988, 1987-1988 (Box 13, Folder 98)
  - Conferences: CHART Directors' Meeting, 31 October-2 November 1988, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 99)
  - Conferences: CHART Directors' Meeting, 4-6 April 1990 (Box 14, Folder 100)
  - Conferences: CHART Directors' Meeting, 10-12 January 1992 (Box 14, Folder 101)
  - Conferences: CHART Directors' Retreat, 17-21 April 1991 (Box 14, Folder 102)
  - Conferences: CHART Directors' Retreat, 29 April-5 May 1992 (Box 14, Folder 103)
  - Conferences: CHART Directors' Retreat Volume I, 29 April-5 May 1992 (Box 14, Folder 104)
  - Conferences: CHART Directors' Retreat Volume II (1 of 2), 29 April-5 May 1992 (Box 14, Folder 105)
  - Conferences: CHART Directors' Retreat Volume II (2 of 2), 29 April-5 May 1992 (Box 14, Folder 106)
  - Conferences: CHARTicles, 12-16 February 1993 (Box 15, Folder 107)
  - Conferences: CHARTicles Portfolio (1 of 4), 1993 (Box 15, Folder 108)
  - Conferences: CHARTicles Portfolio (2 of 4), 1993 (Box 15, Folder 109)
  - Conferences: CHARTicles Portfolio (3 of 4), 1993 (Box 15, Folder 110)
  - Conferences: CHARTicles Portfolio (4 of 4), 1993 (Box 15, Folder 111)
  - Conferences: CHART Project Directors' Meeting, 14-16 October 1993 (Box 15, Folder 112)
  - Conferences: Chicago Education Research Meeting, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 113)
  - Conferences: Denver Education Research Seminar, 11 June 1992 (Box 15, Folder 114)
  - Conferences: Diversified Assessment in Social Studies (1 of 3), 9-12 January 1992 (Box 16, Folder 115)
  - Conferences: Diversified Assessment in Social Studies (2 of 3), 9-12 January 1992 (Box 16, Folder 116)
  - Conferences: Diversified Assessment in Social Studies (3 of 3), 9-12 January 1992 (Box 16, Folder 117)
  - Conferences: Education Funds, School Districts, and Restructuring Seminar, 14-15 April 1992 (Box 16, Folder 118)
  - Conferences: Education Funds, School Districts, and Restructuring Seminar Correspondence, 1992 (Box 16, Folder 119)
  - Conferences: First Seminar on Education for a Diverse Society, 7-8 January 1991 (Box 16, Folder 120)
  - Conferences: Public Education Fund, 15 February 1991, 1990-1991 (Box 17, Folder 121)
  - Conferences: Rockefeller Foundation Invitational Conference, 13-15 November 1986 (Box 17, Folder 122)
  - Conferences: The "I" Word: Institutionalizing CHART (1 of 2), 21-23 September 1989 (Box 17, Folder 123)
  - Conferences: The "I" Word: Institutionalizing CHART (2 of 2), 21-23 September 1989 (Box 17, Folder 124)
  - Conferences: The Next Phase for CHART Pittsburgh Educators Seminar, 16 July 1992 (Box 17, Folder 125)
  - Summer Institutes, 1991 (Box 17, Folder 126)
  - Summer Institutes, 1993 (Box 17, Folder 127)
  - Oversize, 1; 1 box(es) 1 box
    This section contains the single box of oversized materials from the collection, which consists of three folders of photographs.
    - Africa in the U.S. Classroom: Seminar (oversize), 7-9 March 1990, 1990 (Box 22, Folder 159)
    - Conferences: CHART Directors' Retreat Volume I (oversize), 29 April-5 May 1992 (Box 22, Folder 160)
    - Conferences: CHART Directors' Retreat Volume II (1 of 2) (oversize), 29 April-5 May 1992 (Box 22, Folder 161)
- Public Relations, 4; 1.47 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes, 1 legal document box, and 1 half-legal document box
  Series 4, Public Relations, includes all of CHARTs public relations materials from 1987-1994. Formal information kits from several years, which were sent out to interested parties, are in this series, as well as books, newspaper clippings, and other instances of CHART appearing in the media. Also included is communication between CHART and two different public relations firms or managers, first M. Booth and Associates and later Lenore Greenberg.
  - Advisory Boards for CHART Projects, January 1992 (Box 18, Folder 128)
  - Bibliography of CHART Public Relations, 1987-1993 (Box 18, Folder 129)
  - CHART History and Description, 1988-1989, 1992 (Box 18, Folder 130)
  - Greenberg, Lenore, April-September 1992 (Box 18, Folder 131)
  - Greenberg, Lenore, October 1992-January 1993 (Box 18, Folder 132)
  - Greenberg, Lenore Proposal, March 1993 (Box 18, Folder 133)
  - Information Kit, 1988 (Box 18, Folder 134)
  - Information Kit, 1989 (Box 18, Folder 135)
  - Information Kit, 1990 (Box 18, Folder 136)
  - Information Kit, 1992 (Box 18, Folder 137)
  - Information Kit Correspondence, 1989 (Box 18, Folder 138)
  - Information Kit Correspondence, 1992 (Box 18, Folder 139)
  - M. Booth and Associates, 1987 (Box 18, Folder 140)
  - M. Booth and Associates, January-June 1988 (Box 18, Folder 141)
  - M. Booth and Associates, July-December 1988 (Box 19, Folder 142)
  - M. Booth and Associates, January-June 1989 (Box 19, Folder 143)
  - M. Booth and Associates, July 1989-March 1990 (Box 19, Folder 144)
  - Public Relations, 1987-1988 (Box 19, Folder 145)
  - Public Relations, 1989 (Box 19, Folder 146)
  - Public Relations, 1990 (Box 19, Folder 147)
  - Public Relations, January-June 1991 (Box 19, Folder 148)
  - Public Relations, July-December 1991 (Box 19, Folder 149)
  - Public Relations, January-May 1992 (Box 20, Folder 150)
  - Public Relations, May-December 1992 (Box 20, Folder 151)
  - Public Relations, February-March 1993 (Box 20, Folder 152)
  - Public Relations, April 1993 (Box 20, Folder 153)
  - Public Relations, May-June 1993 (Box 20, Folder 154)
  - Public Relations, July 1993 (Box 21, Folder 155)
  - Public Relations, August-October 1993 (Box 21, Folder 156)
  - Public Relations, November 1993-January 1994 (Box 21, Folder 157)
  - Newspaper Articles, 1990-1993 (Box 21, Folder 158)